This task is about activity diagrams, and
we have been given the following properties
where we shall complete action sequences.
Action sequences are from the initial node
to the final node or the ones that are searched
for here.
And we have been given the activity diagram
as well.
Below here, we have the activity diagram of
this task, and we see that we have different
activities within our diagram from A to G.
And there are also conditions on some points
here.
We have been given a first task of generating
a sequence where Y never holds.
When we consider this diagram, we see that
there is for instance X and Y and besides
X and Y we have Z here as well.
And when you create the first action sequence,
Y shall never hold.
And as these activity diagrams were introduced
within the lecture by the ability of being
translated into Petri nets, we have also a
representation of the translated Petri net,
so this activity diagram translated into a
Petri net.
And we can use the pipe tool here in order
to check our sequences later or create sequences
as well when we generate these sequences.
This is not part of the task to generate the
Petri net but of course, if you like to solve
it that way, it would also be reasonable.
But we can also solve the task by just looking
at the activity diagram.
I may start with the first task which was
A, and we have to give a sequence now.
Our sequence has to start with A, no matter
what we're doing, we have to start with A
because the starting point is right here and
A has to be completed anyway.
And our sequence continues with B, as there
is no other part we can do because just another
path joins in, so we have no decision to make,
it's simply B that follows.
And then we have a fork here into different
paths.
And we have to execute multiple paths here
because there's a join at the end again which
of course, is required for this fork.
But we can see that one path is independent
here, it does not rejoin here.
So D might execute it, or might not execute
it.
It doesn't matter if it is when we join back
together.
But we have to execute the other paths here,
so we have to execute C and there is also
E and F.
We have in principle a choice here, but as
the task said that Y shall be false, also
shall not be valid the whole time,
we cannot choose
F here.
But besides that, we can choose any sequence
for C, D and E. Let's for instance say the
next action that’s executed is E and then
only the next activity will be C. Now we have
the option of choosing D or not choosing it
as well.
We could say also D is finished any time or
we just simply say we step right out of here.
And because Y shall not hold the whole time,
we have only the option to say Z holds here
and that we finish with G.
This would be a sequence for the first task.
And let's continue with the second one.
This one says a sequence containing D, but
not E, that is as short as possible.
For our second path, second sequence, we have
to start it same way again.
We have to choose A and we have to choose
B. And we shall again, once more what's written
into task, so it has to contain D but not
E. As it should not contain E, we might as
well choose F as a first
part of the sequence.
We might choose F here for instance.
It should not contain E. That was part of
what was mentioned.
Again, we could also choose C and D here.
Well, we have to choose C, it could have
been first as well.
It could have been before F. The order does
not matter here.
And we want to have sequence which is as short
as possible.
We should not choose D because this would
get us a longer sequence.
I’m sorry, we have to choose
D because our task says so.
We have to choose D which I will choose right
here, D. And finally, we can join those paths
again because we have used this path and we
have used this path as well.
G can be next here in the sequence.
And then after G, the whole sequence is finished.
And now there is a last task for this one,
which is C and we shall search for a sequence
of length longer than nine, in which Y holds
until D was executed.
Our sequence shall be longer than or
equal to 9, and we have to think about what happens
to Y until D was executed.
This is C now.
We start by choosing A here and then B because
that's what we have to do.
Let's just for a moment switch to the Petri
net so that we already have a look at what
we've done with the tasks before.
I switch back to task A which was simply having
a sequence during which Y never holds.
When you have this Petri net here, we can
simply fire sequences and the Petri net gives
us certain limitations on what we are able
to do.
As we see, we could fire A first and it was
only B that we could fire.
Now we have to fire the fork here, which is
of course, no activity.
But anyways, we have to fire it in a Petri
net.
And now we can choose the
other activities here, so C, D, E, F.
We have no limitations in our Petri net on
these preconditions here for X and Y for instance.
As this condition said, we shall not use one
with Y, our only option would be to choose
this path (?herefor, E), as we did right here.
We could have chosen C and D. That's what
I said before, we could have chosen those
first.
But we can also choose C now and we could
choose D when we didn't do it here for a sequence,
but we could do it.
And then the paths are again joined after
the fork.
This part here, the join itself.
Afterwards, we can either go this way up here.
But as we said in the first task, Y shall
not hold the whole time, that's why Z has
to hold and we fire G and are done.
We see in a Petri net, we can also fire D
after we fire G which would not be possible
in the activity diagram because the end is
right after firing G.
We cannot continue from here.
That's the difference we have to keep in mind.
If you want to fire D, you have to do it before
firing G.
But certainly it limits the possibilities
using this Petri net here.
Let's switch you to the Petri net and go back
to the beginning.
Now we can do the second task which was a
sequence containing D but not E that is as
short as possible.
Again, firing A and B is required, then we
fire the fork and now we can choose again.
Again, we have to think of what the task says
because it says that we shall have a sequence
that contains D but not E. In this case, E
would not be in choice because of the task.
We could choose F or C or D as we did here.
Let's do it as we did here.
We choose F, then we choose C. And then we
choose D, remember that, we have to choose
D because it's what our task said.
And finally, we do the join and the G. Well,
remember that the order doesn't matter for our sequence,
the joins could have been before or after
G. And it's only because we have to execute
it here because of the translation of D from
the activity diagram to Petri net.
Now we have checked those parts for the first
task and we can use this one as well to create
maybe the last one now.
Let's go back to the beginning, there we are,
right at the beginning.
Again, we have to choose A and we have to
choose B. Let's check back what our task was.
A sequence of length greater or equal than
nine, in which Y holds until D was executed.
Y holds the whole time and as soon as D is
activated, then Y doesn't hold anymore.
We fired A and we fired B, we activated
A and B in the activity diagram.
Now we fire the fork and in the activity diagram,
we can choose of C, D, E and F. But there
are certain limitations which we should keep
in mind.
First of all, Y holds at the beginning.
And we can choose any of those options in
the Petri net, of course, but the Petri net
does not consider the limitations of our task.
When we fire D, we instantly have the consequence
that Y does not hold any more.
And so we could choose E afterwards only because
we're done, so Y would not hold any more.
I would consider that the
first activity that gets activated here would
be F because Y holds through here.
We have F here.
And after that, we can fire C, activate C
in the activity diagram.
And now, we have to rejoin back here.
And now we could choose G here, which of course
is not useful because then our sequence would
be finished, but it's not long enough yet.
That is why we choose Y here which has no
name here, so Y is still true.
We also have no other choice because D was
not fired yet.
Considering our task, we can even not choose
G which is good because now we have to choose
Y.
And we have to fire B which is here in our
activity diagram, activate B. And now, we
fire the fork again and we can choose for
instance to fire C. So activate C here.
And now we can have a look at how many actions
we already activated here.
It was A, B, F, C, B, C, so we are at six
now, we need three more activities which need
to be activated in order to finish our sequence
with at least nine.
In this case, we could already fire D,
activate D for instance.
Let's consider
D and then we could activate E because Y is
not true anymore, so we have E. And then
we have E and then when we get out, we have
Y as well not considered true, so we can choose
G here.
And then we are done.
I forgot to activate the transition C as well.
We can choose the E, and G and this is the
same sequence A, B, F, C, B, C, D. I have
by accident activated D two times but it could
have been one time as well.
Let me just fix this.
We could have chosen it just a single time
and then we have the same sequence as on the
right hand side.
Thank you very much.